Guide to the photographs by Iraqi civilians collection, 2004 April-May RL.11106
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Photographs by Iraqi civilians collection
2004 April-May
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Archive of Documentary Arts (Duke University)
Daylight
Daylight Community Arts Foundation
RL.11106
4.0 Linear Feet 3 boxes; 1 oversize folder Approximately 507 items
Collection comprises 464 original 4x6 inch color snapshots, 23 13x19 inch color inkjet exhibit prints; roll negatives; and text panels for the exhibit, "Photographs by Iraqi Civilians, 2004." The images are a result of a project, "Iraq From Within," coordinated by the North Carolina-based Daylight Community Arts Foundation, which encouraged Iraqi civilians to document through photographs and captions a point of view unavailable to the foreign press. The original color snapshots, taken by men and women chiefly in Baghdad and Fallujah, show families at home and in their neighborhoods, various workplaces, and scenes of wartime destruction. Taken as a whole, the collection conveys the impacts on men, women, and children of the 2003 U.S. invasion and occupation of Iraq. Acquired as part of the Archive of Documentary Arts at Duke University.
Collection Overview
Collection comprises 464 original 4x6 inch color snapshots taken by Iraqi civilians; 23 13x19 inch color inkjet exhibit prints, selected from the color snapshots; roll negatives; and text panels for the exhibit, "Photographs by Iraqi Civilians, 2004." The collection materials originated from a project, "Iraq From Within," coordinated by the North Carolina-based Daylight Community Arts Foundation, encouraging Iraqi civilians to document through photographs and narrative captions a point of view unavailable to the foreign press.
Using handheld disposable cameras, Iraqi men and women from in and around Baghdad and Fallujah photographed living conditions during the American occupation following the 2003 invasion of Iraq. The images show families at home and in neighborhoods, as well as scenes such as patients and nurses at a hospital, customers and barbers at a barbershop, students and a teacher at a school, a dentist and patient in a dentist's office, men digging graves, a banner hung in the street, and images of wartime destruction. From the initial group of over 460 images, 23 prints by nine photographers were chosen to form the traveling exhibit "Photographs by Iraqi Civilians, 2004."
Acquired as part of the Archive of Documentary Arts at Duke University.
Biographical / Historical
The names of the original "Iraq From Within" project photographers are: Rana Al-Auby, Ammar Abu, Maiid Asraa, Ahmed Dhiya, Ali Feras, Limea Hamza, Sami Haydar, Alaa and Salam Kamel, Jassim Mohammad, Rasheed Saad, Muhamed Salam, Hamed Hasan Salman, Abdulah Samir, Mohamed Shukvia, Mohamed Thamev, Hussam Um, Omar Usama, and Mustafa Ahmed Yaseen. Fred Ritchin and Ambreen Qureshi of PixelPress curated the exhibit, which was displayed August 30 to October 10, 2004 at the New York University Tisch School of the Arts Department of Photography and Imaging in the Gulf and Western Gallery. A selection of images from the project "Iraq From Within" were originally published in the June 2004, Issue 2 of Daylight Magazine.
Exhibit Abstract (by Pixel Press staff)
"The photographs on these walls were taken from only ten rolls of film, all made this past spring [2004] with disposable cameras. The photographers themselves are civilians coming from a variety of walks of life, none having to do with taking pictures: Limea Hamza, for example, is a student in her third year at the English Department of the University of Baghdad, Mustafa Ahmed Yaseen is a cigarette factory worker, Ahmed Dhiya is a dentist, and Hamed Hasan Salam lives in the garbage dump where he photographed his family members."
"There is also Alaa Kamel, who describes herself as 'an Iraqi women of 29 years old, working as an interpreter, living in Baghdad, very much upset about what is happening in Palestine and Iraq, never feel afraid of being a translator...You sent me greetings from America but your country wouldn't like to have me like a visitor there.'"
"Jassim Mohammad is '31 years old with parents and three brothers and sisters. I am looking for a wife. I am an engineer in medical instruments but now drive journalists between Jordan and Iraq. I wish the Americans [at home] could see what they do here in Iraq... The situation in Iraq now is very very bad because we are now like Palestine and Israel...'"
"He, like many others, is also skeptical of recent changes. 'I do not believe this new government are really Iraqis. Mr. Bush is a liar and his troops make trouble and conquer.' But he also says, 'I am sure the American people they are a good people.'"
"The captions are excerpted from texts written by the photographers themselves, slightly edited for the purpose of this exhibition."
"In retrospect, one wonders how photographs by Vietnamese civilians at the time of the war in their country might have enlightened outsiders, or by Jews in concentration camps, or by any group not allowed to represent themselves on the international stage. It has been a year in Iraq during which many of the most important photographs have been made by non-professionals, such as those by US soldiers at the Abu Ghraib prison. These Iraqi civilian photographers, most with no more than one roll of film, also have something to add."
Arrangement
Arranged in the following series: Exhibit Prints; Original Photographs; and Exhibit Materials.
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open for research.
Original negatives may only be used with permission by the Curator of the Archives of Documentary Arts.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Photographs By Iraqi Civilians collection was received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2015 and 2016.
Related Materials
Benjamin Lowy photographs, 2003-2008
Rubenstein Library, Duke University
Documentary Photography -- Iraq; Iraq War, 2003-2011 -- Photographs; Iraq -- Pictorial works; Iraq -- Social life and customs; Iraq -- Social conditions; Family life -- Iraq; Color photographs; Inkjet prints; Iraq War, 2003-2011 -- Personal narratives; Roll negatives; Archive of Documentary Arts (Duke University); Daylight; Daylight Community Arts Foundation
- Exhibit prints, 2004 April-May; 23 prints
  Scope and Contents
  Series houses 23 13x19 inch exhibit-quality color inkjet prints, selected from the many images taken by Iraqi men and women. The prints are arranged in number order assigned by exhibit curator. For the purpose of preservation, prints and exhibit text panels were removed from their original exhibit mats. Exhibit captions and text panels are housed in another box in the collection.
  - This is Hamed Salman's sister, wife, and brother Mohammed. They live in the garbage dump with more than 500 families. Every family has cows that live with them, 2004 April-May; 13 x 19 inches (Box 1, Folder 1, Print RL11106-P-01)
  - This is my Grandfather (Ali Kthyr, 65) and Grandmother (Sadya, 75). They have eight girls and one son, all married. They live in Baghdad, and I went to visit them in my car, 2004 April-May; 13 x 19 inches (Box 1, Folder 1, Print RL11106-P-02)
  - Jassim Mohammad's sister took this picture of her art teacher Eman who is 25 years old and lives in the Al-Bnuk Quarter of Baghdad. The other girl is his sister's friend Shfa'a who is 15, 2004 April-May; 13 x 19 inches (Box 1, Folder 1, Print RL11106-P-03)
  - Zinab is 17 and is a friend of my girlfriend. She lives in Al-Adamia (Baghdad), 2004 April-May; 13 x 19 inches (Box 1, Folder 2, Print RL11106-P-04)
  - Inside Alaa's living room, 2004 April-May; 13 x 19 inches (Box 1, Folder 2, Print RL11106-P-05)
  - Banner reads, "Yes, yes to Islam, Yes, yes to peace, No to terrorism, No to the occupation" (Baghdad), 2004 April-May; 13 x 19 inches (Box 1, Folder 2, Print RL11106-P-06)
  - Abd-Allah, an Iraqi child, is disabled and very sick… there is a device in his head to separate the blood from the fluid that collects in his head… there is an opening in his back… (Baghdad), 2004 April-May; 13 x 19 inches (Box 1, Folder 3, Print RL11106-P-07)
  - In my house which is very very small and had nothing as equipment inside but then we felt the need to buy TV in order to know what is happening to our country (Baghdad), 2004 April-May; 13 x 19 inches (Box 1, Folder 3, Print RL11106-P-08)
  - My friend Riad has something wrong in his stomach and went to Dijla Hospital in Baghdad, 2004 April-May; 13 x 19 inches (Box 1, Folder 3, Print RL11106-P-09)
  - Alaa Kamel and her younger son, Hammodi. She was trying to calm him down since he got scared by one of the bombs that happened in Baghdad, 2004 April-May; 13 x 19 inches (Box 1, Folder 4, Print RL11106-P-10)
  - Child lying on bed (Baghdad), 2004 April-May; 13 x 19 inches (Box 1, Folder 4, Print RL11106-P-11)
  - Inside Al Hussein's classroom (Baghdad), 2004 April-May; 13 x 19 inches (Box 1, Folder 4, Print RL11106-P-12)
  - Tammim works with Ali, the owner of the barbershop in the Al-Sha'ab quarter of Baghdad. Ali is 19 years old and friends with Mustafa who works in the cigarette factory, 2004 April-May; 13 x 19 inches (Box 1, Folder 5, Print RL11106-P-13)
  - About the dentist, his name is Ahmed Sata'a Ra'aft, he is a doctor, he works in a hospital in the morning (8 - 12 o'clock), after that he goes to his house and works again from 4 o'clock to 9 or 10 o'clock. After that time he goes back to his house (Baghdad), 2004 April-May; 13 x 19 inches (Box 1, Folder 5, Print RL11106-P-14)
  - Procession carrying the body of Abass Jassim. Abass was killed by Americans in the war. He left behind a family (Falluja), 2004 April-May; 13 x 19 inches (Box 1, Folder 5, Print RL11106-P-15)
  - Bomb crater, Falluja, 2004 April-May; 13 x 19 inches (Box 1, Folder 6, Print RL11106-P-16)
  - Digging graves, Falluja, 2004 April-May; 13 x 19 inches (Box 1, Folder 6, Print RL11106-P-17)
  - After the girls finish the school there are family members waiting to take them back to the house or they wait for the school bus to take them to the house (Baghdad), 2004 April-May; 13 x 19 inches (Box 1, Folder 6, Print RL11106-P-18)
  - This is my friend, Rua'a, who studies at the school (Baghdad), 2004 April-May; 13 x 19 inches (Box 1, Folder 7, Print RL11106-P-19)
  - Tammim Salim Hussain working in the barbershop. The white mask is facial cleanser, 2004 April-May; 13 x 19 inches (Box 1, Folder 7, Print RL11106-P-20)
  - Abd-Allah, an Iraqi child, who is disabled and very sick, 2004 April-May; 13 x 19 inches (Box 1, Folder 7, Print RL11106-P-21)
  - The worker is building in front of the cigarette factory (Baghdad), 2004 April-May; 13 x 19 inches (Box 1, Folder 8, Print RL11106-P-22)
  - The Iraqi people refuse the new flag and insist on the old one (Baghdad), 2004 April-May; 13 x 19 inches (Box 1, Folder 8, Print RL11106-P-23)
- Original photographs, 2004 April-May
  Series comprises 213 4x6 inch color snapshot prints, with the first folder containing photographs selected for exhibition; the rest are arranged by photographer, and include identification numbers printed on the back of each print at time of processing. Roll negatives are also included.
  The original processing envelopes, one per photographer, contain anywhere from 14 to 24 prints, with the exception of Jassim Mohammad, whose three folders include a total of 52 prints. No envelope was found for the photographer Rana Al-Auby.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Negatives are closed to use; prints are available.
  - Original photographs selected for exhibit, 22 items (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Abu, Ammar, 25 items (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Asraa. Maiid, 25 items (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Dhiya, Ahmed, 20 items (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Feras, Ali, 14 items (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Hamza, Limea, 24 items (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Haydar, Sami, 22 items (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Kamel, Alaa, 18 items (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Kamel, Alaa, 45 items (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Mohammad, Jassim, 23 items (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Mohammad, Jassim, 38 items (Box 2, Folder 11)
    subtitled Falluja 1
  - Mohammad, Jassim, 14 items (Box 2, Folder 12)
    subtitled Falluja 2
  - Saad, Rasheed, 25 items (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Salam, Muhamed, 6 items (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Salman, Hamed Hasan, 18 items (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Samir, Abdulah, 18 items (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Shukvia, Mohamed, 27 items (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Thamev, Mohamed, 25 items (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Um, Hassam, 26 items (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Usama, Omar, 16 items (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Yaseen, Mustafa Ahmed, 24 items (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Original sample photograph envelope, 2004-2005 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Exhibit materials, 2004 April-May; 3 14x17 inch exhibit panels and 16 caption panels (approx. 2x6 inches each)
  - Small caption panels, 2004 April-May; 16 items, 2.25 x 6.75 inches each (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Large exhibit panels, 2004 April-May; 3 items, 14x17 inches each (Oversize-folder 1)